Hello and welcome back to another
video with ItsDrDan and today
we're going to be learning how to
prepare for your lab practical.
So if you're watching this video,
hopefully you're a Chem 3A student.
and you are trying to figure out exactly
how to prepare for your lab practical,
which is probably within the next week.
And you might be a little
bit stressed about it.
So this is my attempt to
try to make a review video.
So this is my first time really making
one for all the students of Chem 3A.
Um, so if you are my student or another
student, then, um, as always, I would
recommend using this video for caution.
If you are my student, obviously keep
watching, but if you're another student,
keep in mind that every professor does do
their practical a little bit differently.
But we do tend to all try to
follow the same general standard
when we're administering it.
So a lot of almost everything I'm saying
should be relevant to you as well.
But make sure you do listen to
your professor exactly how they
instruct you for your video
or sorry for your practical.
So let's go take a look at it.
We're going to dive in exactly
to what to expect for this.
What's the format of it?
And then we're also, uh, whether it's
at the end of this video or in a future
video, we'll dive into the kind of the
major concepts of what to expect in each.
So let's take a look.
All right, let's first talk about what
exactly should you expect when you
walk into your laboratory practical.
The first thing is, is generally
within a week before your practical,
your instructor will assign a
time slot for you to show up.
This activity is an individual
assignment, meaning it's testing
you on your laboratory knowledge.
That you've accumulated over the course
over the entire semester, meaning that
will separate you into two groups.
So being that there are approximately
30 students in a lab section, there will
be 15 that will be in the first half.
15 in the second half.
Now, what does that mean?
So when you assign your time,
you got to show up on time.
So for example, let's say if my
class starts at 11am, that means
half the students will be at 11am.
The other half will be at
1230, which is the approximate
halfway point for my section.
So every section will
be a little different.
So you must show up on time.
That is crucial.
Now, the big reason why is depending on
how fast The actual assignment or lab
practical will start if you show up late.
There's a big chance you will miss parts
of the practical that you cannot make up.
Sometimes you might get lucky and then
maybe you could, you might, if you
miss a station, maybe you can make
it up along the way, but most of the
time you are out of luck and you will
miss those points for your practical.
Now, keep in mind when you show up.
So the second your instructor opens
the door and you're there, You need
to show up not only on time, but
already wearing your, your personal
protective equipment, your PPE, right?
So, which is your lab coat, your
goggles, uh, pants, closed toed shoes.
You need to be wearing those
things ready to go into the
room and to do your assignment.
This can be a part of your grade as well.
There are many instructors
that will take off points.
If you are missing any of these, because
remember this is testing you on your
laboratory preparedness to see if
you know the proper lab skills before
moving on to your next courses, right?
So you need to show up
with those things in mind.
If you forget those things, you could
lose anywhere from, I've seen anywhere
from 5 percent to as much as 50 percent
of the grade that could be deducted,
depending on who the instructor is.
Some instructors will even send you
home, and then you're just out of luck.
So keep that in mind.
You want to make sure you don't do that.
If you have to the night before, put
some extra clothes in your car if you
have to, so that way you have them.
Alright, the other thing is, not to
freak you out, but it's just because it's
serious, right, when you're doing this.
Is you want to, in your lab coat pocket,
put a, your calculator and put a pen or
pencil as well to some, whatever you want
to write with throughout the activity.
So that way you have that ready to go.
Now when you come in, the next
thing is your instructor is going
to let all of you in one at a time.
And assign you a starting position.
It's a, it's what we
refer to as a station.
So you're going to see essentially
stations all around the room.
It's going to go from one through ten.
And there's going to be all these
different spots that are going to tell
you is where you're going to start.
So the first thing you do when you
come in, you'll put your backpack
at the front of the room with your
phone, um, any bags you might have.
Anything that essentially that
you can't use on the exam,
they'll all go by the front.
Then you're going to go to your
station, which then you're just going
to kind of wait and until the start
of the start of the actual session.
So just go there.
Do not touch anything.
Don't talk to anybody.
Just stand there ready to go.
It's supposed to be a very serious thing.
So.
When you're there, just be ready
to work when essentially your
instructor tells you further.
Okay.
So now from there, the way that this
part can work, it depends on how,
when they hand out the versions.
Um, so there are three different
lab practical versions.
You might just get the version when
you walk in, other instructors may
go around the room, handing out a
different color coded answer sheet.
For you to fill out all of your
info, all this, all the, uh,
station info, all your answers on.
And that's going to be the version you're
going to be following the entire time.
So you can get A, B, or C.
They are different colors.
Um, so for example, let's say if I
have B, what I'm going to be doing
is every time I'm at a station, I'm
going to be answering question for
version B at each station as I go.
So you ignore the other versions.
They don't apply to you.
You're doing your own practical,
uh, throughout the entire thing.
So there's going to be multiple different
versions and everybody's going to have
their own, essentially their own tests.
So now when you get there with
that version, you got to keep in
mind that when the timers, when
everybody's in place, there will be
a timer set at the front of the room.
Usually it's shown on the projector screen
where you're always given four minutes
to complete the And then one minute
afterwards, that's like a one minute
warning of after the four minutes to
clean up, to switch stations, to wrap up.
So by the end of the one minute, you
should already be standing or ready
to go at the next station pretty much.
So keep that in mind.
Overall, you have about five minutes
to do whatever it is they need to do.
So when we talk about what
to expect at each station, it
has to be something doable.
In that first four minutes,
there has to be something faster.
So don't try to study all
these crazy things that are
going to take you hours to do.
It has to be doable in a few minutes.
Now from there, let's go
look on to our next part.
So let's talk about how the entire
process works once that timer starts.
So the time has started.
What you're going to be doing is you're
going to just answer your version.
So if I had blue, I'm going to be
answering version B for my station.
So when you're doing this, keep in
mind, the whole station is something
that's doable in four to five minutes.
So when you're studying, you want to
try to be studying concepts of things
that are manageable in that timeframe.
You're not going to be asked to do
an entire experiment in four minutes.
That's not possible.
So when you're looking at
something that's doable.
It's designed to be finished
in that time period.
So if you are someone that's running
out of time, one thing to keep in mind
is just write down the question because
usually you're, you're always given time
at the end to work up your question.
So if, let's say when I got,
when I came into the room, I
was in my lab coat ready to go.
And I was told by my instructor,
you're going to station six.
So what you're going to do at
station six, when the timer comes,
You'll flip over your station card.
It will have the question.
You're going to answer question
six in the number six answer box
on your, on your version sheet.
So it's gonna have one, two, three,
four, five, six, all the way to 10.
You will start on number six.
Now, when you're answering that,
the thing to keep in mind is none
of these are multiple choice.
There are things that you should have
mastered or understood by this point.
Um, or at least ask your
instructor if there's something
that you need further help with.
So all of it is free response questions,
meaning their, their calculations, maybe
balancing, maybe measuring something.
They're all things that you've
been working on throughout
the as you work up your labs.
Now, when the timer goes up, that is
when you'll rotate to the next station.
And typically the way these are
working is that they're always
in increasing order as you go.
So if you start at six, you will
then rotate to number seven.
Now the nice thing is, is you're always
going to be following the same person.
So there's going to be another student
at, let's say, the station next to you.
They're going to be going in front of you.
So you're always going to
follow the same person.
So if I'm at six.
I'm going to follow the student
at number seven the entire way
through as it's increasing.
Now there might be also depending
on how big your group is.
So being that there's only what,
10 stations that are there,
well, if you remember, I said
there could be up to 15 students.
What that means is that there's going
to be something called a rest stop
at different points around the class,
meaning that between certain stations,
there might be a, might be an area
where you can kind of just relax.
For the five minute window of opportunity,
or you can finish up other questions,
so you might see that there will
be some of them and your instructor
will notify you if that's something
they are doing for that session.
Every time it is different.
It depends on whether or not depends
on the number of students in your time.
So at the end of what you're going to
be doing, so you'll do all 10 stations.
Uh, generally this takes about
an hour and a half or so to
hour to an hour and a half.
Um, when you're done, you're usually
always given about five minutes
at the end, just to wrap up your
questions, maybe answer something
if you didn't quite finish it.
Um, just to really, just to make sure
you get as many points as possible.
to pass your lab practical.
So keep that in mind
as you are doing that.
So let's go look at the next part.
So what can we test on
in this entire thing?
Well, there are many things that
we can always test you on when it
comes to chemistry, because as you
kind of learned about this semester,
there's a ton of information.
It is a lot that goes into
introductory chemistry.
Um, so the first thing is, did
you show up properly in lab?
Right?
So wearing that proper PPE and wearing
your lab coat, goggles, all that stuff.
Is one of the first things, you know, does
that tell me that you are that you are
essentially treat lab as a professional
environment because you want to be a
professional one day in your life as well,
where you're either a health care worker,
a scientist or whatever it is, you've
got to wear proper PPE in your career.
So this is something that you
need to be tested on, right?
Make sure you can do that.
The next thing is really, can you
measure, can you do measurements?
One of the most crucial things that
you need to get out of this class
is can you do measurements because
in every career, especially in STEM
or the health sciences, measurements
are the backbone for what we do.
And in many cases, if you don't do
measurements correctly, it can lead
to a lot of different problems in a
lot of different careers, whether it's
lawsuits or maybe even worse, where
someone could get injured or hurt.
So you need to be able
to do the basics, right?
So the first thing is you have to
write down everything you're doing
when you're at these stations.
A lot of times there can be, there's
partial credit that can be awarded at
every station, especially when it comes
to showing your work, writing your
calculations down, showing that you, that
you know something about the problem.
So write down all of your units, write
down all of your significant figures.
Know the basic idea of how to measure
things like tick marks on glassware and
how to actually approximate the number of
sig figs when you're going through them.
Um, so those are going to
be really important, right?
Sig figs have been drilled into
all of you every single day
in every homework assignment.
Of course, it's going to be
a part of the lab practical.
That doesn't go away.
Measurements have to be precise
and need to be accurate as well.
So keep that in mind.
Now the next part is equipment.
Can you name basic glassware
that you use in your labs?
This is the easy point questions, right?
You should know what a beaker is,
what an Erlenmeyer flask is, what
a thermometer is, what a pipette
is, what a volumetric flask.
If some of these names are things
that you don't recognize, then I would
recommend reviewing your glassware.
There's a couple ways you can
do this depending on how your
teacher set up your course.
You might, the one thing is that
there's probably a study guide in
Canvas that has probably flashcards
in it of all the glassware.
The other thing, in many of
our lab manuals, we have a
list of all the glassware with
pictures for you to refer to.
So those are all really useful.
Make sure you're aware of the general
purpose of a lot of glassware.
There were a couple labs where you
might've used something that was really
unique and a little weird, and you
haven't seen it in maybe two months.
So make sure you kind of review and
go through those introductions because
they're going to help you remember
really what it is, read the intros.
Look through the post lab.
See how you did your calculations.
It will help refer your brain to exactly
what you did now with calculations.
One thing you see is like I put a
50 percent with a plus next to it.
Well, the whole idea of reason is
most of this test is calculations.
It's all that's most of all chemistry
is it's a it's a math class in
disguise is what I always say.
So one of the things is all of
your data workup is fair game.
That was the biggest
part of the lab, right?
You spent maybe an hour or two work,
like collecting data and probably five
to 10 hours working up your lab report.
So you need to be comfortable
doing your data calculations.
Now, once again, I'm going to say
this again, it has to be something
doable in four minutes, right?
So it has to be short.
It can't be something
that's really, really long.
So you're not going to be asked to
go from start to finish of an entire
lab going through 20 calculations.
It's going to be something short and
sweet, whether it's like maybe balancing
a chemical reaction, maybe figuring
out the theoretical yield of something,
maybe the limiting how much of maybe do
a limiting reagent calculation, maybe
do a pH calculation, maybe do a gas law
calculation, things you've done in lab.
So it has to relate.
And then the last thing is really
being knowing your terms, right?
You don't want to come to a
station and be like, I don't,
I don't recognize these words.
That's the worst feeling.
Especially if.
You might know it if you were, if
you were reviewing your terminology,
so make sure you remember all
like the different techniques that
were used, at least the basics.
So that way, if you had to perform
something, or if you had to do a
calculation about it, you need to be
able to recognize them, make sure you're
able to know how to use, um, and measure
things based on what's being asked of you.
So there is a little bit of language
and vocabulary that's used all the time.
That could be a little different, right?
Whether it's knowing what
concentration is, right?
What units is that?
That's molarity, right?
You got to be familiar with that.
Knowing if I say, oh, we have this
hydronium concentration or hydrogen
ions being able to connect the dots,
that's going to lead to pH, right?
So there's little things like
that, that you need to make
sure that you're familiar with.
Now, another thing is when it comes to
the calculations and the terms, You're
always, you're always given, uh, reference
materials to help you bridge that
gap, whether it's the formulas you are
given or reference sheets to help you.
So whether it's the Piroc table
or maybe, uh, your green sheet for
knowing your solubility rules, if
it's something that's used in the
problem, it's going to be provided.
So if you're trying to like, think
like, Oh, I need this thing on the,
on the, um, On this question, and
there's a good chance you might be
thinking about it the wrong way.
You could always ask your instructor
a question if you believe something
should be there, and it's not, but I
always feel free to ask, but it should
always be there in front of you.
So be familiar with your resources.
that are available now.
So this entire video, so
this is the end of this one.
So being that this will be part one of
this video, just giving a broad overview
of really what all this is about.
Part two is going to be longer.
It's going to go into the specific
experiments, um, essentially
kind of talking about what are
the overall ideas that you need
to know about and how to really.
Well, like what to look for in each lab,
like what's something that's doable.
So just to kind of remind your
brain of what each one is.
So this was the introduction.
I hope that this does help you
prepare for your practical.
I hope that you pass your practical,
whether if you're my student,
I hope you absolutely pass it.
And if you're someone else's student,
make sure you do check with your professor
that, you know, that you are familiar
with everything that's required of you.
So that way.
you do prepare for it adequately, right?
We all do it a little bit
differently, but we all, we all
follow the same general idea.
Um, so good luck and I will hopefully
see you in part two, where we will
talk about each lab we completed this
semester and the basic idea of what
you could have to solve in each one.